



## Ajay

# DATA SCIENTIST/ MACHINE LEARNING

#### Profile:

5 plus years of work experience as a Data Scientist, including deep expertise and experience with Statistical Analysis, Data Mining and Machine Learning Skills using Python. currently working as a Data Scientist at Philips (Healthcare division).

# **Programing**

- 1. Python: NumPy, SciPy, Scikit-learn, Tensorflow, Keras, OpenCV, Flask, Seaborn, Matplotlib
- 2.R
- 3. **SQL**

#### Others

- 1. Microsoft Excel
- 2. Microsoft PowerPoint

# **Operating Systems**

- 1. Linux
- 2. MacOS
- 3. Windows

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# **Tech Specialist**

- Working as a Data Scientist in Sutherland Healthcare Pvt ltd. from Aug 2021 to till date.
- Worked as Data scientist in Tech Mahindra as a contract employee from Oct 2016 to July 2021

# **EDUCATION**

B.tech in EEE, 2012 JNTU Kakinada.

#### ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

**Technical Skill Set** 

Programming: Rand Python.

Data Base: Queries using open SQL, Basics of DBMS.

Office Tools: Microsoft Office Suite-Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Access, Outlook.

Philips, Bangalore Aug 2021 to Present

**Data Scientist** 





## **Roles and Responsibilities**

- Modern MRI systems in Philips have evolved to be 'smart' i.e. they are coupled with IoT capabilities to dump all the vital signs of the machine on a daily basis to a MySQL database hosted in Azure with the help of ETL processes.
- Successfully deployed a diagnostic tool named CAT (Common Analysis Tool) for MRI machine systems. The CAT framework uses the data dumped by the ETL to the database, and uses certain queries to classify situations which can cause a malfunctioning to the MRI system. There are thousands of such possible failure modes which the CAT can identify within a few seconds, for thousands of systems used in different parts of the world. The core idea is to enable remote monitoring of these systems to reduce the downtime for servicing, which will in turn reduce the expenses incurred by Philips as well as increase the customer satisfaction.
- Perform maintenance of existing machine learning models to remove bugs, increase performance or add functionality.

# Time Inc., NY, US Data Scientist/NLP Engineer

May 2019 to present

**Time Inc.** was an American worldwide mass media corporation founded on November 28, 1922, by Henry Luce and Briton Hadden and based in New York City. It owned and published over 100 magazine brands.

The objective of the project is find out the customers who is going to enroll for the promotion activity and amount of sale giving.

We implemented image classification, and implemented the sentiment analysis.

#### **Roles and Responsibilities**

- Predict the enrolling customers for the promotion activity introduced by client using the classification technique.
- Created territory alignment by considering area sales potential, sales force size and geographical constraints.
- Image classification for the custom dataset with volume of ten thousand images and seven classes solved using deep learning, CNN and Architecture of VGG-19 using Keras models The model showed excellent performance to extract information from given context.
- Work with NLTK library to NLP data processing and finding the patterns.
  - Designed and implemented Sentiment analysis using Python NLTK library

## Cardinal Health, Dublin, Ohio, US

Nov 2017 to May 2019

#### Data Scientist/ Machine Learning Engineer

Cardinal Health, Inc. is an American multinational health care services company, and the 14th highest revenue generating company in the United States. Its headquarters are based in Dublin, Ohio and Dublin, Ireland.

Objective of this project is to implement better insights into their employee attrition problem.

And to find out the cancer present or not from given clinical records of the patients.

## **Roles and Responsibilities**

- Data analysis, creating work plans, programming in R, creating presentations for the client.
- Designed and Implemented HR Employee attrition predicted using the Machine learning Algorithm in R statistical tool.
- Developed a model on Cancer detection from the given data using Classification technique.





- Tested several models to predict whether a given records represents the categories.
- Create Data Quality Scripts using SQL and Hive to validate successful data load and quality of the data. Create various types of data visualizations using Python and Tableau.

Ge oil and Gas , Hou, Tex Data Analyst Oct 2016 to Nov 2017

GE Oil & Gas was the division of General Electric that owned its investments in the petroleum industry. In July 2017, this division was merged with Baker Hughes. Objective of this project is to giving insights from the data using exploratory data analysis.

## **Roles and Responsibilities**

- Communicated and coordinated with other departments to gather business requirements.
- Gathering all the data that is required from multiple data sources and creating datasets that will be used in analysis.
- Performed Exploratory Data Analysis and Data Visualizations using R, and Python.
- In Preprocessing phase, used Pandas and **Scikit-Learn** to remove or impute missing values, detect outliers, scale features, and applied feature selection (filtering) to eliminate irrelevant features.
- Conducted Exploratory Data Analysis using Python **Matplotlib and Seaborn** to identify underlying patterns and correlation between features.
- Used Python (**NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, SciKit-Learn, Seaborn**) to develop variety of models and algorithms for analytic purposes.
- Setup storage and data analysis tools in Amazon Web Services cloud computing infrastructure.